<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[0 .A.Dventure]]></title>
  <link href="http://github.com/sathyamvellal/0adblog/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://github.com/sathyamvellal/0adblog/"/>
  <updated>2013-10-14T01:52:24+05:30</updated>
  <id>http://github.com/sathyamvellal/0adblog/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Sathyam Vellal & Jashwanth Reddy]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The source of it all...! [Part 2]]]></title>
    <link href="http://github.com/sathyamvellal/0adblog/2013/10/07/the-source-of-it-all-part-2/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-07T13:14:00+05:30</updated>
    <id>http://github.com/sathyamvellal/0adblog/2013/10/07/the-source-of-it-all-part-2</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In the last post we documented an overview of the game and also some vital resources that are to be used during the game-dev So lets start descending into the source. In this post we&rsquo;ll discuss how the game starts and runs.</p>

<p>Also, you can access the doxygen generated doc of the game&rsquo;s source available <a href="http://github.com/sathyamvellal/0adblog/docs/index.html">here</a>. This documentation will be regularly updated and will be referred to throughout the blog.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>If you build the game on your own, using the source, you typically get a binary <code>pyrogenesis</code> in the <code>binaries/system</code> directory and the game will be using data or scripts present in <code>binaries/data/mods/public</code>; unless the game is compiled with some flags specifying the binary, data or lib directories while setting up the workspace (info can be found <a href="http://trac.wildfiregames.com/wiki/BuildAndDeploymentEnvironment">here</a>).</p>

<p>So let&rsquo;s begin! When the game is run, it starts off by performing some initializations.</p>

<ol>
<li>The thread on which the game started is marked as the main thread and its named &ldquo;main&rdquo;. <a href="http://github.com/sathyamvellal/0adblog/docs/GameSetup_8cpp_source.html#l00827">[GameSetup.cpp:827]</a></li>
<li>The current time is noted so that elapsed time can be counted from this point. <a href="http://github.com/sathyamvellal/0adblog/docs/GameSetup_8cpp_source.html#l00838">[GameSetup.cpp:838]</a></li>
<li>The profiler is initialized and started. The profiler is used for analysing framerate fluctuations or glitches and temporal relationships between threads. <a href="http://github.com/sathyamvellal/0adblog/docs/GameSetup_8cpp_source.html#l00842">[GameSetup.cpp:842]</a></li>
<li>The locales are set for the game execution depending on the OS. <a href="http://github.com/sathyamvellal/0adblog/docs/GameSetup_8cpp_source.html#l00844">[GameSetup.cpp:844]</a></li>
</ol>


<p>After this is done, the game is then ready to start running. Now,</p>

<ol>
<li>The command line arguments are interpreted (if any given). <a href="http://github.com/sathyamvellal/0adblog/docs/main_8cpp_source.html#l00446">[main.cpp:446]</a></li>
<li>A virtual file system is created and the game&rsquo;s cache and data are loaded. <a href="http://github.com/sathyamvellal/0adblog/docs/main_8cpp_source.html#l00465">[main.cpp:465]</a></li>
<li>The game is now started and the graphics initialized. <a href="http://github.com/sathyamvellal/0adblog/docs/main_8cpp_source.html#l00504">[main.cpp:504]</a></li>
<li>The input handlers are initialized and set. <a href="http://github.com/sathyamvellal/0adblog/docs/main_8cpp_source.html#l00506">[main.cpp:506]</a></li>
</ol>


<p>By now the game is up and running and the profiler would be capturing every frame.  When the game is quit, the shutdown sequence starts. You can see all this starting from <a href="http://svn.wildfiregames.com/public/ps/trunk/source/main.cpp">source/main.cpp</a> and related files. There&rsquo;s just too much code to inline in the post!</p>

<p>While this certainly gives a fair idea of how the game begins, its worth noting some classes and features available in the source.</p>

<p>The Core Engine modules are placed in <a href="http://github.com/sathyamvellal/0adblog/docs/dir_0dc38aac9085a57339423d7e064a603d.html">source/ps/</a> directory. A few of them are &ndash;</p>

<ol>
<li><a href="http://github.com/sathyamvellal/0adblog/docs/ArchiveBuilder_8h_source.html">ArchiveBuilder</a>: Used to package mod files into distributable archives.</li>
<li><a href="http://github.com/sathyamvellal/0adblog/docs/CConsole_8h_source.html">Console</a>: The in-game scripting console.</li>
<li><a href="http://github.com/sathyamvellal/0adblog/docs/ConfigDB_8h_source.html">ConfigDB</a>: Manage configuration variables for the game.</li>
<li><a href="http://github.com/sathyamvellal/0adblog/docs/CStr_8h_source.html">CStr</a>: A string wrapper designed to provide better string handling.</li>
<li><a href="http://github.com/sathyamvellal/0adblog/docs/Filesystem_8h_source.html">Filesystem</a>: A class to provide filesystem-like functionality to the API which makes it easier to access files for the game.</li>
<li><a href="http://github.com/sathyamvellal/0adblog/docs/CmdLineArgs_8h_source.html">GameSetup/CmdLineArgs</a>: A class to parse the command line arguments.</li>
<li><a href="http://github.com/sathyamvellal/0adblog/docs/Paths_8h_source.html">GameSetup/Paths</a>: Wrapper class for OS Paths used in the game.</li>
</ol>


<p>&hellip; and many more! You can have a look at <a href="http://github.com/sathyamvellal/0adblog/docs/dir_0dc38aac9085a57339423d7e064a603d.html">the directory</a> to view all the files in it.
Our work isn&rsquo;t done yet! Our initial focus has been on the AI which we&rsquo;ll be covering next.</p>

<p>To be continued &hellip;</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The source of it all...! [Part 1]]]></title>
    <link href="http://github.com/sathyamvellal/0adblog/2013/10/02/the-source-of-it-all-part-1/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-02T07:38:00+05:30</updated>
    <id>http://github.com/sathyamvellal/0adblog/2013/10/02/the-source-of-it-all-part-1</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>We finally made an attempt to go through the source and wow its big! One thing about OpenSource projects is how much you learn by understanding the source; not just getting to know it but learning and understanding the design concepts! <a href="http://svn.wildfiregames.com/public/ps/trunk">This wiki page</a> tells you what to do to get the source and how to build it.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>This post is aimed to give you an overview of some aspects of developing 0 A.D. Although these details are available in the wiki, they are not yet structured in an understandable way. Here, we gather many wiki articles and also provide some information on how the game is structured.</p>

<h3>What does the root directory contain?</h3>

<p>Let&rsquo;s have an overview of it first.</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span>Root Directory </span></figcaption>
<div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
<span class='line-number'>8</span>
<span class='line-number'>9</span>
<span class='line-number'>10</span>
<span class='line-number'>11</span>
<span class='line-number'>12</span>
<span class='line-number'>13</span>
<span class='line-number'>14</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class=''><span class='line'>(0ad)source@svn : /$ tree
</span><span class='line'>.
</span><span class='line'>|-- binaries/
</span><span class='line'>|-- build/
</span><span class='line'>|-- docs/
</span><span class='line'>|-- libraries/
</span><span class='line'>|-- source/
</span><span class='line'>|-- license_dbghelp.txt
</span><span class='line'>|-- license_gpl-2.0.txt
</span><span class='line'>|-- license_lgpl-2.1.txt
</span><span class='line'>|-- LICENSE.txt
</span><span class='line'>`-- README.txt
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>5 directories, 5 files</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p><strong>binaries →</strong> This contains all of the game&rsquo;s data, scripts that are executed during the game, mods and other executables (typically for windows). This is what goes to the end user.<br/>
<strong>build →</strong> This has the necessary tools and programs to set up a workspace to build the game. More instructions on how to build the game can be seen <a href="http://trac.wildfiregames.com/wiki/BuildInstructions">here</a>.<br/>
<strong>docs →</strong> All documentation goes here.<br/>
<strong>libraries →</strong> Placeholder for third-party libraries used in the game. However, they may or may not be used.<br/>
<strong>source →</strong> This contains the source of the game engine and the source of other tools that are associated with the game (Eg: The scenario editor).</p>

<h4>Are there more details available?</h4>

<p>A more detailed information on what these directories (and their subdirectories) contain can be found <a href="http://trac.wildfiregames.com/wiki/Finding_Your_Way_Around">here</a>.</p>

<h4>What resources are available for a contributor to learn more about the game?</h4>

<p>The first is the <a href="http://trac.wildfiregames.com/">trac wiki</a>. This has a lot of links for all kinds of contributors &ndash; artists, programmers, etc. The next place are the <a href="http://www.wildfiregames.com/forum/index.php">game forums</a>. One needs to register for the forums and there are 5 categories of forums available; the description of which can be seen under the link to the particular forum. And lastly, the best place to communicate is the IRC. You can join the channels<code>#0ad</code> and <code>#0ad-dev</code> in <code>QuakeNet</code> and jump right into a live discussion over there!</p>

<h4>What are the languages used to implement the game design?</h4>

<p>The source of the game is written in C++ and JS. Interesting right?<br/>
The convention is to have as much of the game&rsquo;s source in JS as possible (to keep it simple) and only write the core game engine and those components which need performance in C++. This enables the game to be heavily moddable through JS.</p>

<h4>I would like to be a developer and was wondering how to start with the game-dev. Any tips?</h4>

<p>As we said, the <a href="http://trac.wildfiregames.com/">trac wiki</a> is the entry point for getting a picture of the game&rsquo;s structure. The next step would be to start reading the source (which is discussed from the next post onwards). You&rsquo;ll also need to know the <a href="http://trac.wildfiregames.com/wiki/Coding_Conventions">coding guidelines and conventions</a> that are followed so you can understand the source better and also will get you prepared when you start with the development. You would also need to learn <a href="http://svn.wildfiregames.com/public/ps/trunk">how to build the game</a>, which for a developer, is vital. You can then look at some <a href="http://trac.wildfiregames.com/report">tickets available on trac</a> and try to solve a few easy ones. This actually kickstarts the development and helps you to learn more about the internal structure of the game. You can start off with a few <a href="http://trac.wildfiregames.com/query?status=assigned&amp;status=new&amp;status=reopened&amp;keywords=~simple&amp;col=id&amp;col=summary&amp;col=status&amp;col=type&amp;col=priority&amp;col=milestone&amp;col=component&amp;report=16&amp;order=priority">beginner-level tickets</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Why we're contributing to 0 A.D.]]></title>
    <link href="http://github.com/sathyamvellal/0adblog/2013/09/22/why-we-are-contibuting-to-0ad/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-22T09:37:00+05:30</updated>
    <id>http://github.com/sathyamvellal/0adblog/2013/09/22/why-we-are-contibuting-to-0ad</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><strong>Age of Empires</strong> is A game by Ensemble Studios which revolutionized the RTS gaming industry which is still played by millions round the clock! But it did not stop with the Age of Empires series. Many more historic RTS games have come up in the past decade; Empire Earth, Rome Total War, etc. And here&rsquo;s one that is coming out soon!</p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>What is 0 A.D. ?</h2>

<p>0 A.D. is a historical Real Time Strategy game being developed by Wildfire Games. It all started by a collaborative effort of three modding communities in 2001/2002. You can read <a href="http://play0ad.com/about/the-story-of-0-a-d/">The Story of 0 A.D.</a> to know the full story. The game was open sourced in July 2009 and has been quite a star in the open source gaming world.</p>

<h2>Who we are.</h2>

<p>We are a team of two; myself, Sathyam M Vellal and my teammate Jashwanth Reddy M and we have enrolled into &ldquo;Architecture of Open Source Technologies&rdquo;, an elective being offered in our college. This elective requires us to contribute to an open source community through the semester and we decided to contribute to 0 A.D.</p>

<h2>Why 0 A.D. ?</h2>

<p>Every open source community has its share of awesome developers and mentors. What makes this better? An open source community developing a game. Nearly half the community is online most of the day and developing some feature. What I like most about this community is the relaxed discussions they have. Its serious, yet fun and fun, yet technical. Well, if these aren&rsquo;t enough, I have an excuse to play the game any time I want now! Even during class! By the way, the game has amazing graphics; have look at <a href="http://play0ad.com/media/screenshots/">some screenshots</a> and it has an <a href="http://play0ad.com/media/music/">incredible soundtrack</a>!</p>

<h2>0 A.D Docs and Info</h2>

<p>The developer devil &ndash; Documentation. Nobody wants to write it, yet everyone wants to read it. Although 0 A.D. is not too different from others in this regard, the game is still highly structured with information present online to help a developer start his work. The <a href="http://trac.wildfiregames.com">root of all info</a> is <a href="http://trac.wildfiregames.com">trac</a>. And there&rsquo;s always <a href="http://webchat.quakenet.org/?channels=#0ad-dev">IRC</a> for everything else.</p>

<p>This blog is for us to record our adventure in exploring and contributing to 0 A.D. Stay tuned for more updates!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
